welcome everybody to the fourth episode
of active inference insights I'm your
host Daris Pary Wayne and today I have
the pleasure of Hosting inz hippolito
inz is a lecture of philosophy of
artificial intelligence and mqu
University in Australia our research
focuses on 4E cognition which holds that
cognition is embodied embedded enacted
and extended beyond the brain and she
studies how this framework can help us
understand and build other systems that
exhibit a form of augmented Mission
including brain computer interfaces
neurot Technologies and smart
environments in addition to this she
co-founded the international Society of
the philosophy of the Sciences of the
mind with gutier picini and she is
currently the ethics uh ethics advisor
um in artificial intelligence versus the
cognitive Computing company which
implements active inference into
artificial intelligence agents um inz
thank you so much for joining me it's an
absolute pleasure thank you so much for
having me uh the pleasure is mine and
it's um we were just discussing off a
that you know we're doing this across
many oceans so Nez is in Australia I'm
in London um but we managed to sync it
up which is which is fantastic exent so
I wanted to start with markof
blankets um all things start with Mar
Markov blankets um Mark of blankets
really play a fundamental role in active
and in the framework that we apply to
artificial intelligence to cognition
more generally and also just the
underlying physics and math of back to
inference and a lot of your work has
focused on Mark of blankets and the
scaling up of Mark of blankets so maybe
a good place to start for our audience
would be if you could just give a simple
overview of exactly what a mark of
blanket is and then we can go from that
yeah fantastic uh yeah you're absolutely
right when you say that everything
starts with the mark of blanket
everything that is a thing um is has got
a mark of blanket and that does not
necessarily mean um that a mark of
blanket is going to correspond to a
certain kind of like physical boundary
that one can see uh right a mark of
blanket um is a theoretical formal
construct that what it does is it tells
you um how or what things are going to
be influencing a certain state to be the
case right so it's it is a statistical
Tool uh precisely to understand
something really important uh which is
how a certain thing is coupled with
within or with its environment um so
everything does start everything has its
markco blanket does start with the
markco blanket because it is a way in
which we can
capture two very important aspects um
and these two aspects um are that um a
thing um typically an open system as the
thing um is um both thermodynamically
open and operationally closed so this is
quite crucial um because it is what
allows the thing um to persist not to
perish not to succumb to the second law
of
Thermodynamics so Mark of blanket is
really become uh very useful because to
my understanding um they allow us to
capture simultaneously these two
features being both operationally open
oh sorry operationally closed and
thermodynamically open because what
happens is the system is situated in the
environment in a way that it is open to
the environment it must be coupled with
the environment otherwise it is uh
perishing um it will not maintain itself
but it also has a certain boundary that
allows it to maintain its coherent for
so the markco blankets become really
interesting because they allow us to
capture those two dimensions of um an
open system and what is an open system
an open system is mostly everything that
we see uh we don't really come across uh
closed
systems excellent yeah that's great um
I'm wondering whether you could give us
a sort of overview of exactly how that
coupling works so people may have seen
that the mark of blanket is essentially
composed of active States and sensory
States um that makes sense if yet if
we're talking kind of about physical
boundaries like actuators arms legs and
so on but on the understanding The Mark
of blanket is a statistical
entity what does um what what what
really are active States and sensory
States um in the theoretical way well
there are many ways to answer this
question um it will depend on how much
you want to connect um then the active
inference framework and formalism uh
with other uh theories that we find in
physics or in Neuroscience uh so there
are many different ways in which one can
answer um this question um but for the
sake of remaining um with the kind of
like more scale-free application of
markco blankets and not reducing to
immediately uh to the brain um I will uh
keep the formalism as something that we
can apply to understand the statistical
relations or
influences um between a system an open
system and its environment um right so
then what you have is you have the
possibility of understanding how a
certain system is in a particular state
so you understand that and then and then
what you can also understand is you can
make predictions about future States in
which you may find the system by virtue
of using this kind of for formulas right
uh so then what you have is you employ
or Define that the level or aspects um
of scientific interest are going to be
your internal States right and then your
next question is going to be okay how do
I find this system in this PR in this
precise uh time and space in these
particular States what are the the the
the states uh in which the system is
situated that are going to be crucial
for me to find the system in this
particular State and therefore I
understand um the system and potentially
ideally I can make some uh nice
predictions about future States so this
will be our internal States so then what
we need to we need to get on is then we
need to get to Define what are the
external States and those are like I
said the states that are going to be
influential uh for immediately
influential for um the system to be in a
specific kind of like internal States
now this is all done the next step is to
understand that internal and external
States they mutually influence one
another that's what it means about
something being an open system right is
that there is exchange of mattera and
energy such that the system is remaining
in a certain State and for example is
not um going into into a face space um
uh such as like perishing or or towards
um towards uh death um so then um what
what you get is an understanding of um
what I was just saying which is how the
system is coupled and in this permanent
um continuous exchange of matter and
energy in order to remain
alive and push back on the second LA
themodynamics right so you get this
operationally closed and open system at
the same time that is uh very well
captured by these internal and external
States and I did say that uh they
influence one
another but it is important um to
understand that they do not directly
influence one another they need a second
set of States um so basically internal
and external states are conditionally in
opin it and they will require the
intervention of a second um set of
states which is very much what you asked
uh the active and sensory States right
so these are going to be the ones that
are doing the direct communication if
you will between each other where um
hopefully and ideally we have um a
balanced influence between sensory and
active States right and these um direct
influences between um sensory and active
states are going to play a crucial role
in order for us to mathematically trap
down and understand the coupling of the
system in the environment which is the
system being internal States the
environment being external States so
this is just like the overview of uh the
mark of blanket and the active inference
formalism that we could apply to
anything that is an open
system wonderful yeah that's great
that's a really useful explication of
the framework um I think it's as I kind
of hinted to in my initial question it's
it's rather easy to think of it as a
physical boundary so we can think of
cell boundaries or the blood Bane
barrier or the boundaries of my body and
then when we do that the notion of sense
reactive States really becomes intuitive
in the sense that in the case of my body
all it is is an action perception Loop
and that's being known to be critical to
intelligence or cognition for a very
long time
so that said there's also a very strong
position which is that it's actually
just a statistical description of the
way things act the way things persist
through time that leads me to ask the
question of should we consider the
markco blanket to be in uh interpreted
in an instrumentalist way in the sense
that it's kind of a way it's a tool that
we can use in modeling objects open
systems or is it or should we be inter
in it in a realistic way I.E there is
actually something uh that is
ontologically a mark of blanket that is
truly out there as a markco blanket um
embedded within lots of other markco
blankets of course yes I'm really glad
that you ask that uh question it's a
Live question um and um there are many
ways to answer um this question so the
way that I that I that I that I decided
to answer the previous question was was
in a way that one understands that um a
mark of blanket is a tool is a
statistical tool it's a formalism it's a
mathematical construct
right and I also did not go immediately
into the brain uh or an organism with
actions and Sensations because I'm
trying to avoid uh precisely um the
literature that tends to reduce the
framework to thinking that active States
and sensory states are going to be
action and
sensation right that is not the case
right um so a mark of blanket formalism
from active inference can be applyed to
anything that is an open system and
there are many um examples of this in
the literature such as for example I can
think of um the example of when you have
a set of um of pendulums in a room or a
set of clocks in the same room what's
going to happen is uh that eventually
they will synchronize right and you can
use this framework to capture to predict
that synchronization right so it is
important to understand that this is a
mathematical construct that you can
employ to precisely understand patterns
of behavior in the natural world right
so we've done that um we understood that
so then we can think about it you can
use this uh framework to develop for
example simulation models which allow
you to understand the phenomenon of
scientific interest as well as hopefully
it's a good model is going to give you
some prediction power over future states
of the thing which doesn't have to be uh
anything to do with cognition can be
something um uh that is situated in the
natural world right then a certain
phenomenon happens specifically in
cognitive science when we notice that
specifically in cognitive science even
if you apply a certain computational
framework doesn't have to be active
inference a certain computational
framework is applied to model simulate
for ex and get some predictive power
about for example black holes let's say
black holes right uh and they use that
kind of like mathematical
framework and then you employ the same
kind of mathematical framework the same
kind of like ationalism to understand
the brain because after all both a black
hole and uh a brain are complex systems
what does that mean it means that it is
extremely difficult for us to model it
why is it extremely difficult to model
it because it is very high in dimension
so it's really hard for us we don't have
the computational power to to model it
which is why we need to incorporate
something called uh dimensionality
reduction because we don't have the
tractability to to Pro precisely do that
now keeping up with what what I was
saying in cognitive science
specifically a phenomenon happens so
imagine this we use the same
computational um strategy to model
things from the natural world all the
way to the brain right and then what
happens is that we would never say that
the brain had sorry that the the the
black hole or something that is not uh
part of uh a living system would have uh
specifically a mark of blanket or would
engage in literally active inference we
would understand very clearly that this
is computational strategy that we are
developing and employing for epistemic
purposes to understand the phenomenon
and to get some predictive power that's
what we're doing and we are happy with
it if we get some predictive power
that's success in
science and then one once we do this
move and apply exactly the same
formalisms into for example the brain or
an organism right we tend to
anthropomorphize it right so we tend to
say okay so then the brain is acting
precisely literally by engaging in
active inference or in other uh Realms
engaging in predictive coding right so
we lose track of understanding that okay
these were the tools that we started off
with and we were very happy when we were
modeling black holes with these tools we
were happy that we had some predictive
power but now it's not enough we won't
more well now we want to go from The
epistemic Virtue into an ontological
predictor now we want to say that the
thing that we are modeling trying to
understand developing um uh models for
epistemic gain is precisely has the
properties or the ontological properties
that the model the computational model
has right and that's when you get into
making a realist or taking a realist
stance on and upon active influence
right you don't have to you can do it
but then you're going to have to defend
that position in a way that okay you're
going to have to answer so if you are if
you are applying the question that you
need to answer then is if you're
applying exactly the same framework to
model and predict black holes that you
want to do the same with
brains do you get to say that brains
engage literally in active inference in
ways that black holes don't and why so
that's the realism take and the problems
that you find and what where you would
uh be led to or you remain in the more
cautious kind of position which is on
the instrumentalist or non-realist
position in which case the position is
that all
things in the world with with with the
real existence right and those things
behave in ways that we would develop
models to understand that behavior in
terms of patterns patterns of
behavior the things exist in themselves
they interact with the world in
themselves the patterns of behavior are
our scientific
constructs so then we talk and then we
can start talking about okay so I can
pattern behavior through for example
employing developing a model on the
basis of Maco blankets active inference
and then I pattern the behavior what did
I did what I did was I found patterns
and therefore an explanation for a
Behavior Uh and this explanation is
something that I didn't have before
right right right right well I'm going
to take us towards some realist position
now because I think people will find it
interesting about the
the ontological claims ontological
implications uh that act of inference
has especially within the cognitive
science and the Neuroscience community
and I guess when you're taking a real
stance on the Markov blanket that there
are these structures which have some
kind of um embedded nature in the brain
right and and people have probably heard
frisen talk about how this is actually
reflected in the phen phenotypic nature
of the brain and its
hierarchies um it makes me think about
modularity so mod it for people who
don't know was introduced by Jerry Fodor
um in
1983 and the basic idea is that modules
are these kind of um innate neural
structures which have kind of very
specific functions and fdor in 83 laid
out sort of certain category certain
functions that they a modular system
would have to um you know would have to
obey by so domain specificity the fact
that modules have to operate on a very
specific type of input um there's also
informational encapsulation this idea
that like at least how he portrayed it
in 1983 that these modules are
encapsulated with respect to high
orderer
beliefs that that notion got sort of you
know weakened over time let's say and
then there were further about the actual
neural architecture would have to be
involved in mod uh modules but anyway
people can get the basic idea
um of a module we might have a visual
module a hearing module a module for
language right which would yeah which is
idea clearly taken up um or that tronsky
found a lot of joy in um all that to say
what does active influence have to say
about this picture of the Mind as being
modular to any interesting degree and
does this notion of kind of at least for
predictive coding position position a
hierarchy in which you have feedback
loops in which the top down affects the
bot the top layers affect the bottom
layers and vice versa does that actually
really have anything to say about
modularity and more generally the
architecture of the brain yes um well
I'm really glad that you you're taking
us there we do have um a couple of
papers that do um engage a little bit
with uh the modularity of the Mind one
of them is Mark of blankets in the brain
and that paper and the the one is
parcels and particles um and um in there
we do briefly mention
um reasons why thinking uh or patterning
the the brain Behavior the brain
activity in terms of markco blankets
would be useful for many reasons uh for
for for for applications that go all the
way to DCM uh dynamical caal modeling in
in Neuro Imaging but I'm going to set
that to the side and I'm going to
specifically speak to uh the modularity
of the mind you very well said um the
modularity of the mind is is one of the
is one of those um theories that we've
been having in philosophy of mind that
has been very foundational for cognitive
science and for the ways in which we ask
questions for the ways in which we look
for things in the brain um and has been
uh as influential as it has been refuted
uh so very few people today I can think
of three people people uh that would
endorse good old school fodorian
modularity of the mind and there are re
there are philosophical reasons for that
and there are scientific reasons for
that philosophically uh there's been
made very substantial solid strong
arguments against it and uh
scientifically um evidence shows
neuroplasticity shows neural reuse in
ways that would contradict uh the
modularity of the mind I will make here
just a recting of a little bit of
history of philosophy of mind just um
before I get into U the active inference
um understanding of um cognitive SLB
brain um activity and Dynamics just to
say that it's interesting to see that we
have this tendency so I'll do a little
bit of philosophy of Mind here we have
been having this tendency in philosophy
of mind or at least analytic philosophy
of mind um which is to look at and this
is a point that has been made by many um
influential philosophers
uh for example Francis Egan um she has
made this very uh clever point and I
think she's absolutely right when uh we
look into World philosophers of Mind
look into what is happening in computer
science and then we adopt the best
computer science at the time to
establish a kind of like a metaphor to
how the mind supposedly work at the time
as you said in 83 uh Jerry F looked at
um uh touring machines and in he and he
asked the question what would happen if
one would conceive the mind as if it
were a touring machine and then he
writes the book right what happened is
that what starts off as being like sort
of like metaphorical thinking right it
eventually starts becoming a very
ontological uh claim that the mind is
ontologically modular and that is very
um it's very important for us to look
back in history so that we know what to
do and what not to do in the future
right because what happens is then you
set off cognitive science to look for
those modules in the brain as you set up
experiments as you set up uh uh uh
simulations computational simulations
you set off to look for and find those
very um then you have all of those sets
of properties that are supposed to be
the model so there's the automaticity
there's the domain specificity there's
there's the information encapsulation
there's the top down information oh
sorry uh the B
information going all the way up to
cognition cognition mean so all of that
framework that was a theoretical
framework adopted from computer science
then is defining the whole cognitive
science field and what we should look
for right so it's quite interesting and
important for us to know our history to
know how things really happen in a way
that well you look back and and you see
how how it then science came back and
said well it kind of actually doesn't
make sense that the mind is modular in
that way uh so not only philosophically
we have refuted it and very u in ways
that we have forced the modularity of
the mind to reinvent itself to revise
itself to survive really and what
happened was um because the problems
were coming to arise from philosophy and
from from from Neuroscience what
happened was we started having to revise
the modularity of the mind because the
noveles were coming up but we did not
want to let go of the modularity of the
mind so we start revising the basic
pillars and then we start having to let
go of basic pillars and that's when you
have massive modularity by petas for
example and still um challenges continue
to come up right so then you start going
into this other uh this other field
which was known at the time um cognitive
penetrability so now what you allow is
you you you you revise modularity to the
point that it's not just bottom up
information going up but now you will
allow for bottom up and top down that's
cognitive penetrability right and then
it comes up um around
2010 and stays until 2020 still is a
little bit here because as we um sort of
like um explored a little bit in a in a
in a special issue that we we we just
had out um this year with Michael kof
it's a special issue in Consciousness
and cognition and it's about uh the bean
brain and how whether how or whether uh
the visian brain predictive coding is
compatible to the modularity of the mind
and specifically to uh the one that
allows the this traffic going up and
down um such as uh cognitive
penetrability and there are still um a
few people that um very are very engaged
um in defending that kind of um of
modularity of the mind that is um quite
um agreeable and comp comptible with
predictive coding and examples of that
are for example more conservative um uh
approaches within U predictive
processing theories of the mind for
example the predictive mind prediction
error minimization uh mostly developed
uh and headed by um by yakob Hui um that
would be one that um you can find as as
as having some agreement with with
modularity of the mind of course the
revised version
of it which is uh the one in which uh it
is it allows traffic to go up and down
and that's of course you can see the
parallel as it being predictions coming
down prediction errors coming up and the
traffic being very contentful in nature
therefore you have a version that it has
got this compatibility between
modularity of the mind and um and um and
the the predictive uh brain what happens
is and I'll just wrap this up and go um
then to active inference what happened
there if you think about it is you let
go of two things that were very precious
for Jerry fer you let go of horizontal
boundaries and vertical boundaries and
once you let go of that you really have
to ask the question what is left of the
modularity of the Mind why should we
keep it in place at all whatsoever right
because what happened was you let go of
one there was the basic pillar of of the
modularity of the mind which was the
boundary that was a distinguishing or
dividing uh cognition on top and modules
at the bottom right this boundary
doesn't you don't have this boundary
anymore because now you have predictions
coming down so you let go of this
boundary
so Jerry doesn't get that and they have
the vertical boundaries as well which
were very precious because those were
about information encapsulation such
that different modules are the main
specific and they do not talk to each
other right so what you is you get rid
of those vertical boundaries there's
there's an interesting there's an
interesting historical point there um
that just sorry to interrupt but this is
an interesting there there's an
interesting chronology here which I
actually learned during my undergrad
where when I was looking at whether the
language comprehension was fundamentally
modular so it was related that's hence
why I brought up n jsky in 83 fodal has
very distinct definitions of information
encapsulation and Dom specificity so do
specificity is actually what we just
spoke about that there's a proprietary
database that each module works on right
so visual the visual module work on uh
photons or whatever you know or the
language module works on syntactic
nodes and information informational
encapsulation in 83 was top down beliefs
expectations doesn't affect the workings
of those modules interestingly in in
2000s so he he writes another book or or
article about modularity in the year
2000 he kind of conflicts and again I
don't want to speak ill of Jerry fodo
he's very important and he's also not
here anymore so he can't defend himself
but he seems to confuse information
encapsulation with dom specificity
because he talks about like this is a
quote that a system is encaps a module
is encapsulated if it's restrict if it
function is restricted to what its
proprietary database contains so I think
what's interesting there is factly what
you're were talking about in terms of
horizontality and verticality kind of
abandons the verticality there right he
wants to uh yeah he he abandons the
verticality in the sense that by by sort
of a mission he concedes that maybe we
should let go of this idea that top-
down beliefs expectations don't
influence lower levels he does keep the
um the horizont horizontality which is
let's keep these as distinct systems
working on discrete um languages or data
for ones of a better ter so so it's just
an interesting historical fact there
that I think if he was H frodel might um
he could obviously offer some
clarification but may also go back on
his original 83 position of top down um
the the restriction for top down
information to flow into modules yes
absolutely and um I think that this is
also how you are absolutely right um in
in in specifically the point about the
conflation between information and caps
olation and the main specificity these
are two different
things and one of the things that are
that one of the aspects that I think
would would need to be abandoned and
that we abandoned in our Mark of
blankets in the brain is precisely that
notion of
information right so because you can
have domain specificity without relying
on this notion of information
encapsulation and things not conversing
with each other because again to my
perspective that is anthropomorphizing
the brain and brain activ ity right
we're talking about Dynamics and
activities of the biology kind in the
brain and there is an
anthropomorphization uh that I don't
think it's necessary and again it proved
itself
unnecessary right um so um but but we
learn so much from from learning the
history of where these ideas come from
and they have a place of course U and I
think it's important for us to precisely
learn where they come from such that we
start um improving and advancing our
understanding of uh the brain and
cognition in different ways so there is
definitely place for for for Jerry Fodor
um and I think that this is the place is
to get us into other other other uh
advancements in the field and what um
what we have been able to to to to to
see and uh through scientific evidence
in in in neuroscience precisely that
that kind of way of thinking that may
have started as a metaphor doesn't
really hold right and that there may be
um domain specificity I think you put it
in a very nice way there may be domain
specificity without it being information
encapsulation right and once you start
having to let go of all of these basic
pillars of modularity it's gone we can
try to salvage it and then call it
something and brand it something else
but it's gone and that's when then you
also see in the history well we have now
new um computational uh capacity or
strategy such as parallel distributed
processing what shall we do let's try to
apply the same thing that we did which
is what if we would think about the mind
as if it were a parallel distributed
processing system and then you have the
networks and predictive processing theor
start rising up on the base of that
analogy as well I am careful about going
over and abond and above the anal the it
being a metaphor right because I always
think about the brain as a very
biological kind of system as opposed to
a full agent with full capacities that
thinks and reasons and models as if it
were a scientist so I push back on that
I'm careful about that so the way from
that position on then the way in which
we theorize Mark of blank blanket is
being useful
was you start from those understandings
that the brain is a dynamical complex
system right that it
changes over time that the ways in which
a full agent engages with the
environment is going to have
significant impacts on the ways in which
pathways are strengthened or are
weakened in the ways in which the brain
is going to develop itself as an organ
right
so you start from that very
neurobiology kind of understanding of
the brain that it is a complex system
meaning that it is a coupled system it
is situated in a body it is situated
within other organs uh in in in the
organism and this organism is situated
in the environment right so we we we
completely abandon the view of the brain
as being a predictive machine there even
though you can and there's lit chore on
building upon the idea of the brain
which of the brain being a predictive
machine which comes from from Helm holds
and more recently you can theorize it
and I've been um I've been presenting on
that as you you can theorize it as the
low road or the high road to active
inference which we can talk about later
but the view is you can take that
pathway that's not the one that we took
uh we took the pathway of the very
neurobiology uh kind of way of the brain
being a highly situated organ within a
larger system the larger system being
situated in an environment and all of
these influences and interactions are
going to have an effect on the state
that you're going to find the brain in a
specific uh uh um point in time and
space so so then um starting from that
understanding as opposed to the brain
being a a machine uh right so then we
ask the question of whether or not uh
because this is what this is crucial
this is the crucial point which is why I
started by by describing mark of blink
is is this scientific construct that you
can apply skill free comes skill free uh
that you can apply to anything that is a
thing there is an open system you can
apply it you can also apply it to the
brains but then you once you do that you
have to test it out right you have to
look into okay does this really make
sense can we
find patterns of
activity that would be explainable
through the application of Mark of
blankets at different levels of
organization within the brain itself so
then in that particular paper what we
did was we we are we start from a
standpoint where we reject the
modularity of the mind because we do not
think that there are reasons scientific
reasons to think
that the the the the the brain is
organized in very strict rigid ways call
it modules whatever we want to call it
but in very strict rigid ways we do not
think that that's the case because there
is scientific reason not to take that
path and the Brain being a very Dynamic
and changing um system then the question
that you have is how do we make sense of
it right how do we find patterns in such
a dynamical system in such a coupled
system how do we find those patterns can
we find those patterns so then let's
apply this um uh Mark of blanket
formulas
at different levels given the data that
we have coming from DCM coming from
dynamical causal modeling of the brain
so basically um in very very simple
terms The View here is that we put the
brains in Scanners we get data out of
the scanner and then we look at that and
just vast data the comic sense of it Con
and start to think about how to make
sense of that you employ DCM as a model
to make sense of that data and what you
would get get from that is a nice causal
topology about how um uh uh how
connections are made and Dynamics are
formed so you get a nice pattern of that
if the model is is is is suitable and
useful then you that's what you get so
then from that kind of like um
scientific um point we we we grab all of
that all of those nice models uh from
DCM and we see we look at whether or not
we could apply the mark of blanket
formalism so the four the two sets of
States um internal and external active
and sensory States in order to uh get an
explanation of those pattern Dynamics at
different scales so we start off with
the the scale of a single neuron and
then we have a cical column and then we
have regions right and what is the what
is the the the take on message from this
because of course if if anybody's
interested uh in the details then the
paper is out there um but what is the
take on message there is that we do find
the same patterns of behavior across
scales by virtue of employing this uh
formalism and that is that is really
good that's already quite um quite quite
quite important because that means that
you can get what we started off our
conversation with you can get um
understandings of activity that is
occurring in the brain at different
scales where uh each of those scales is
both operationally closed and
thermodynamically open so then what you
get is you let completely go of that
rigid systems that you had with the
modularity of the mind you completely
let go of that and what you get is an
understanding of how um certain neurons
in in in specific um environments you
can think about it in a very simple way
as like a cell in a Cell tissue how a
cell in a Cell tissue is interacting and
engaging with the tissue in order to do
what it needs to do um so you can think
about you can use this formalism to
precisely understand how that particular
system is behaving according to the
environment that it is at so then you
find these patterns of behaviors of like
certain neurons firing given certain um
conditions and then you get all this
nice understanding of discou Behavior
being situated that is highly Dynamic
and it really is dependent on the
environment that it is situated at what
you also realize is that there are
certain parts of the brain there are
certain specific parts of the brain um
that you can see that they may be
insulated that they they they do not um
conform to um active inference they do
not
exchange um and that's in a way if you
wanted to say that would be what Jerry F
had in mind as a modularity of the mind
you could say that but all that happens
there is a very simple bi biology
process which is the system already
knows what to do without needing to know
what is going on in the environment it
is what we say as it is set by Evolution
it works so it's been working so well
that way that it doesn't need to know or
get to know feedback from its
environment right so those would be the
ones in which you would say oh it's
encapsulated but it's informationally
encapsulated I wouldn't say
so right right right right yeah there's
a lot of that there's a lot of that um
cool I mean it I you also gave a really
nice um description of for cognitive
science there so exactly as I said in my
introduction um the four e for those who
can't remember embodied extended see if
I remember enacted extended you get all
of them yeah um and I'm enjoying the
history lesson as well so um because I
do as as you said I think the chronology
is really important here just to get a
picture of the philosophical foundations
on which this work is being done but
eight years after Jerry Fodor releases
the modularity of the Mind the very
important book comes out which is the
embodied mind of Raa Thompson and rash
before we go there because you work I
guess within that framework of as you
said for cognitive science the embodied
mind I think listeners will be curious
about you you mentioned scientific
evidence refuting uh
modularity I just wondering if you could
provide this maybe just with one example
of a module which is not exhibiting the
typical um the typical features that
Fodor laid out which would make it
fundamentally modular so what what makes
it open let's say to its environment
yeah one very clear example comes from
the all the research in neural reuse so
that would itself already um sort of
like move us away or it's it's I would
say it's it's strong reasons to move
away from that rigidity of modules that
are do not change that are um as Jerry
fod would conceive of it they are
hardwired in that way so another feature
that you lose is the automaticity right
so the idea with the auto automaticity
is that modules in a way are silly right
they don't know really what's going on
they are hardwired to automatically
process the information that they domain
specific to right so that's the automat
automaticity they don't really have a
say in the meta so to speak um even
though I'm completely anop anthropomorph
ing this story as as one would with the
modularity of the mind uh so you you do
lose that um with with with the the the
large evidence on on on um on neural
reuse where you see um which is
extremely compelling and it it's
absolutely fascinating that you see
certain neurons that we used to be
neurons for vision to become neurons for
something else like like odit Tre system
for example depending on the necessity
of the whole overall
system so what you see is the neural
reuse um uh cases where well it really
it really challenges the basic aspects
or properties that would make a module a
module right don't make domain specific
or is it domain specific if it becomes
the main specific to something else uh
the automaticity um as well so the the
the the neural reuse um I think would be
a it's it's a great challenge um another
one is of course neuroplasticity so the
studies in neuroplasticity do um
challenge again the rigidity of uh the
the the the the non changeability of
this hardwired um system yeah absolutely
okay great that's really useful yeah
yeah I always think about um I think I
got to about the murk effect when I was
learning about modularity of mind
which is this auditory visual illusion
that when people yeah people can search
up or do the murk effect but again that
that brings into question um this
encapsulated idea that muls can't speak
to each other okay excellent well as I
said what became very popular uh after
these kinds of rigid computational
accounts of the Mind was an activist
embodied models following verel Thompson
and rush and verel was of course a
biologist
and so um and he introduced the term
aesis which kind of means this self
organization that we now speak of or
self- evidencing um before 1991 so so as
you were saying we are inclined now to
look at the brain as a biotic thing as a
biological system and this is very much
uh for grounded in um embodied cognition
maybe it would be useful for everyone if
we could just go through the four e
firstly um it doesn't it doesn't have to
be super it's a very rich history um so
I'm you know as long as short as is
suitable but maybe we could go yeah one
by one and think about where is the
evidence or where is he philosophy or as
the intuition that this is true um and
we can start I guess with the the first
one which is embodiment what what does
embodiment mean and kind of what is the
research around the embodied brain what
what does it focus on what does does it
Center on all right very very good um so
um embodiment is um something that is is
a concept that comes from phenomenology
um from the existentialist Philosophy
from phenomenology it's a very rich uh
concept and it is fundamental to
understand a lot of confusion in the
field because we need just we need to
distinguish between weak and strong
embodiment I will call strong embodiment
the one that comes from chology and
existentialist philosophy such as the
one that for example Sim B had in mind
the body that one has that grounds our
experience of the world that's the kind
of embodiment from SIM
or um and um then within the E
Frameworks uh within the E framework you
have different theories and while they
do agree with let's say a couple of um
principles they are going to disagree
age with within certain more nuanced
aspects of their own theories and I
think the embodiment is one that is
mostly useful for us to understand the
State of Affairs in the field and the
theory and the confusions right so um
let's say that it is very reasonable to
to think that most people in the field
of cognitive science today are not going
to reject that the body plays a role to
understand the brain that the body plays
a role to understand cognition very few
people would disagree with this right
the followup question is how do you
understand the body and I will get to
that I will just say that only those
that would conceive of cognition as
encapsulated in the brain as a computer
system such as the prediction error
minimization accounts or for example
yakob who is kind of conservative
account um that there he says very
clearly you can throw away the body the
world and other people because the brain
sufficiently as a machine takes care of
the cognitive business so that would be
the only account that I know of that
would not bring in the body to play a
fundamental role all other accounts do
agree I think we have come to that
agreement that the body plays a
fundamental role embodiment plays a
fundamental role now the question the
follow-up question is how do conceive of
embodiment and then you have two ways
the weak and the strong weak embodiment
is the one that is endorsed for example
by um predictive processing theories
such as Andy Clark as the Visionary uh
behind it what happens there is that
Andy Clark in his account invites the
body to play a causal role in cognition
and this is important because also with
the with the with the with the with the
body you can um interact with a world
that is Technologic iCal where there are
things that then give you the extended
mind but I'll I'll get to that if if we
have the time anyway so it's weak
embodiment what does this mean this
means that um cognition is a predictive
processing that takes place in the brain
so this agrees with more conservative
predictive uh aor minimization accounts
but not only in the brain predictions
but the prediction processing machine
includes the body what does this mean
this means that the body is seen as part
of the predictive machine the body is
seen as computational cognition is
computational so that's why this is weak
embodiment so anic clar does not endorse
the embodiment that MTI or Sim had in
mind he endorses a very computationalist
kind of embodiment so this is why you
can kind of like to understand the E
cognitive science you kind of have to
spread it out within a range and then
you get like um you get like the more
conservative ones and the more radical
ones right the more conservative ones
are the ones that are going to say that
cognition is computational the more
radical ones are going to say that
cognition is not computation and then
you have a spread out of of um of the
question that you can ask to help
navigate the ecognition uh literature is
how radical do you want to be
because if you want to say that
cognition is computational you're not
radical at all right and radical doesn't
have anything to do with original
radical just means how radical you are
in comparison to Old theories such as
the the the computational theory of mind
what is the computational theory of mind
is everything we' been talking about
with the modularity of the mind and
predictive processing theories this is
all computational theory of Mind how
radical are you in relation to the
computational theory of Mind where are
the basic assumptions are to that
cognition comes down to um uh
computational processes of information
processing that's computational theory
of mind and that the mark of the mental
is mental
representation there would be more
Nuance thing things to say but this
would be two that you can ask yourself
and then you can ask how radical am I
away from these two assumptions right so
that's the view and then you get like
this weak embodiment which is very close
to or if not it is um kind of like right
in the border between computational
theory of mind and ecognition almost
like shouldn't be there if you would
conceive that uh cognition within e the
E umbrella is not computational right uh
so that's the very weak embodiment and
then you have the strong embodiment
which is any theory that explains
cognition by grounding cognition very
much uh within the embodiment that the
experience that one has of the world of
course here what we talking about is uh
the level of analysis and and
understanding that uh people working in
that field are looking at is um about
the full um agent that is situated in an
environment we are not talking about
neurons of course we take that into
consideration in the sense of the causal
relations that I mentioned before which
is how is it that the experience of the
world is going to aect effect and
influence the Bly biological processes
and in there you also find the brain so
that's kind of like the strong
embodiment from mopon H and all of that
kind of thing uh that we have and mostly
applies to uh psych Psychotherapy and
and and and psychological analysis and
then you get into um uh let's say in
activism right and then in an activism
you find um different kinds again but
let's say that both strong embodiment
and in activism they reject these two
things they reject that cognition is a
computational process of information
processing uh and they reject that the
mark of the mental is mental
representation so they reject these two
things right they reject in kind of like
different ways but non not
non-compatible but they they they want
to reject these two assumptions um so
the an activist um has different
different ways um in which uh you can
also formulate of it um so you have the
verela Thompson and rush so verela and
Matana uh starting the autopoetic um uh
in
activism uh which is a very rich uh
literature very based in in biology and
extremely compelling uh and very well
formed um and then of course um others
more recently pick up on um autopoetic
and activism and uh they have developed
more recently um the framework towards
uh sense making uh in activism now I
want to just stop here to go to autois
just to make the bridge with active
inference where you can right where or
at least where I find that it's
reasonable to make that breach um
autoptic and activism um brings out and
a lot of recent work by an activists
they also stress uh that out um they
bring out the understanding of crucial
aspects of living systems from bacteria
to us um as having those two aspects as
being thermodynamically open and as
being operationally closed and those two
aspects Lounge the system into a state
of precariousness so these are main
Concepts within theop poetic and
activism and what this can then mean
that we can think of is that what does
it mean for a system to be precarious
well what it means is that the system
must must must interact with the
environment in order to remain alive
what does this mean well this means that
the system is coupled with the
environment now again what does this
mean this means that the system the
living being cannot be encapsulated from
the environment what this would refute
is the conservative computationalist
views that cognition comes down to being
encapsulated in the brain and we can
throw away the body the world and other
people so that's kind of like what this
means so that's why the question is how
radical are you from The View that
cognition comes down to computations in
the brain right how radical are you so
we're making our way towards a more
radical one and then once you find these
ideas of like operationally closed
thermodynamically open therefore a state
of precariousness therefore must be
coupled otherwise it dies then you say
well this active inference framework
actually captures that very nicely
because I get conditional independency
from internal and external stat that
would allow me to get the operationally
closure but I also get the direct
influence of being thermodynamically
open that comes from active and sensory
States so then it really nicely captures
that state of precariousness as a tool
so that's that's nice I think and then
you can um you can go as radical as you
want which is to completely push back on
um any views or kinds of theories or
ways of thinking that would bring out uh
cognition and cognitive systems from
bacteria to more sophisticated
inculturated systems like us um as um
being computational of any kind and this
is something that I've been presenting
as augmented cognition in the in the
sense of
um the kinds of like computational
models that we develop um and
mathematical thinkings that we develop
they are our cultural PR practices right
so in that sense we developed these very
sophisticated ways of making sense of
the natural world of which brains are
part of living systems are part of right
we develop all of those very highly
sophisticated systems and computational
um capacity um to make sense of the
world around us and what I'm very very
careful is not to make that last step
which would bring me back to the
computational theory of mind to say that
those computational strategies are
ontological predictors of what the brain
is of or or of what the living system is
so I am very careful about that that
maybe put me in the very radical
position because I reject all of the
computational theory of mind uh view um
so that's how you kind of like make your
way within the ecognition is by asking
how radical are you in respect to to
computational the of
mine excellent great um I think we have
two more e but we but we basically
touched upon them um one is
embedded um and the next one is extended
um do I give a brief absolutely word to
that absolutely so um the embedded one
is the one that as I was spre spreading
it out in range and I was saying that
well um you have here very close uh you
have a bound with the computational
theory of mind and here you have the
radical stuff so embedded is here close
to the the the computational theory of
mind and this is the E that I mentioned
before when I explained that um very few
people in com in cognitive science in
the field would reject that the brain is
embedded in the body and the body is
embedded in the environment very few
people would reject that so that's the
embedded that's why this can be seen as
almost close to the weak em embodiment
that's the embeddedness very few people
would talk about
encapsulation only with that exception
of the one that is the prediction
rization by Yakov can throw away the
world um and other PE the body and other
people so that's the embededness is just
the claim that the body is the brain is
situated in the body the body is
situated in the environment now then how
you are going to explain that
situatedness is where you are going to
fall in different ease in the strong
embod
in the different kinds of uh in activism
the radical in activism or the more
sense making in activism um how you are
going to explain that it's the
embeddedness is what's going to make the
difference on our radical you go and
then you have the extended which I
briefly mentioned um so the extended
comes as a part of like a package uh
with um uh radical predictive processing
by and Clark so the package is that um
it it is it is radical in uh relation
and in comparison with prediction and
minimization um or conservative one it's
radical in relation to that but it's not
radical in relation to other eats so
what happens is that what you have is an
understanding of cognition as being a
computational process that takes place
where well not only in the brain but
also in the body right the body plays a
causal role for that information
processing predictive processing to
occure and to happen uh in the ways that
it does now it can also incorporate
objects tools from the environment that
are going to play a causal role of the
same kind as um your body plays so then
you have a whole system that is
distributed it's is a computational
system we still talking about
computational theory of mind it is a
computational system that involves brain
body and
tools and that's the extended
mind great um and yeah I always feel the
need to kind of refer people to where
these ideas come from so um extend of my
hypothesis Clark and Chara's classic
paper um and definitely worth checking
out I think when I hear uh these
stronger an activist or stronger for
recognition um perspectives which refute
representation as the mark of the mental
or Mark of cognition it makes me think
uh where does Consciousness fit into all
of this because as a conscious
um you know subject uh being with a
subjective start upon the world I you
know I I have some sympathy for the enti
list view because I think it feeds into
some intuitions that I can't like this
mind is privileged and can be divorced
in some sense from the world upon which
it does some computational work so if
really we we we take the privilege away
from
representation um
which which I think is also a kind of
worm so we don't have to get into
exactly what is a
representation but maybe we maybe we can
go there um what's what's the kind of R
of qualia subjectivity intentionality
and the kind of uh features of
Consciousness oh thank you for that
question I always feel like when um when
we go that path um the mental
representation being the mark of the
mental um it feels like uh we are
getting to watch a TV show halfway
through like in season two right because
we don't ask the questions where the
representations and content comes from
right so that's the hard problem of
content so I know that we want to get
that because that would allow us because
we already are in the place where we do
have me we can engage and develop and
more and more every more sophisticated
mental representations that what we are
that's what part of what we are doing
here is engaging in ways in which we are
involving and employing uh mental
representation such that we can
understand each other right so it's like
we're already half season halfway
through this through the TV show we are
already like in season three um so but
there was a beginning of the TV show
right well you didn't have any of this
you as a baby as an infant could not be
communicated with me in this way about
these things where does that come from
that comes from something called
inculturation right so I think before
before we start explaining things as if
they were always like that we need to
understand that there is a trajectory in
cognition in cognitive development that
we shall not forget so all of those
things had to be acquired unless you
want to defend
nativism that that would be also could
could be very close to Jerry F as well
because you already have these starter
packs that you already have this very
very much in place um Machinery that
would allow us you to have all of these
sensory all of this semantic content
already ready to use that you could
start making sense now if you reject
folder you reject it all now you have to
answer the question how can we do this
where does this come from you've
rejected folder right so you have a
story to tell now the way that I I see
it and many um in activists do see it uh
and by the way also very much compatible
than with mathematical uh Frameworks of
dynamical and complex Theory um and that
is that is employed in in in a lot of
psychology uh uh Empirical research as
opposed to the computational theory of
mind uh even though that's the
mainstreaming in cognitive psychology
it's not the only one um and the way in
which you can think about it is that you
um cognition the m so what I'll start by
saying this I've I've heard many times
people ask me but how is it possible
that there's cognition but there is no
no mental representations no one is
saying that so that's not a claim that's
not a claim from an activist an activist
an activists don't say that there aren
mental representations what they tell
what they want to tell you is that
mental representations do not come for
free you are not born with them you had
to do things in the environment in order
to acquire them you have to to develop
it as a skill so we give you a story
about a hard problem of content where
does that come from when it does not
come as within the nice starter pack
that cherry foder or decart would tell
you that it comes from so once you get
rid of that you have a story to tell and
the story is that it depends on
inculturation so basically as you start
as an infant as a baby we we come into
the world and we start interacting with
the world this world is and this is the
key point this world is already social
it's already a social cultural setting
there is no baby that is born and is
developing within a setting that is not
social already so it is in the ways in
which the baby interacts with the their
caregivers that the parents are the
caregivers and the world around them
that is going to gradually allow them to
build um simpler um Concepts simple ways
of using Concepts and then scuff holding
that into a a numerical system in a
conceptual framework and then later on
in being able to engage in logical
thinking and reasoning and then being
able to express some sophisticated ideas
and maybe even becoming a scientist and
contribute to developing highly
sophisticated computational models that
study black holes so it's an
inculturated process of course as we are
here doing this interaction um what we
are using is we are making the best use
of our most skilled to so far uh and I'm
sure that um that will go keep going in
a in a in a a trajectory but our best
skills of um explaining ideas and
discussing so we are using and making
the best use of our best mental
representations but I also have to say
that this interaction does not reduce to
those U mental representations there is
an embodiment aspect of the situation
that we are at a a very clear uh example
of that is that the interaction is
different whether or not we are having
the interaction in person or we are
having the interaction online we'll make
things different because we don't share
the same physical space so this is just
an example of um how embodiment here
would play uh uh uh some some would play
out but the idea is that eventually
you'll start developing the capacity to
develop and engage in mental
representations also as you talk to
other people and you make sense of the
world around
you okay cool um I'm going to play not
going to play Devil's Advocate but um
and I also don't want to make you commit
to any position nor am I asking you to
solve the hard problem of Consciousness
because that's not that's not going to
happen this also not the purpose of the
podcast but I understand in that sense
that mental representations are kind of
Downstream on enacted behavior on social
cultural norms right it they as you say
there's a lot of evidence to suggest
that it's not some hardwired Chomsky and
module right there we can take that as
kind of
axiomatic I guess my question here is
that kind of makes sense in terms of
mental representations per se let's say
they develop out of this inactivist um
way of being that we have what it
doesn't necessarily answer is the kind
of characteristic features and the
idiosyncratic features of
Consciousness so the actual like
fundamental what it is like to be me
what it is like to be you to use Thomas
Nagel's terms so I guess my question
here is
um again not trying to pin you down I
understand there's a lot of nuance
here would the an activist be uh sort of
would they be attracted to the notion
that Consciousness is epip phenomenal
and by that I mean for people who don't
know epip phenomenal Consciousness is
the idea that Consciousness is like the
steam coming off a steam train so it's
caused by uh neural physiological
Behavior but doesn't actually have any
causal effect on those um on those
mechanisms so it happens it's there
right and it kind of depends on what
philosophy of Mind Theory you um
subscribe to but would they say that
Consciousness has no causal role um I'm
imagining that there aren't many
substance dualist in activists but what
what what kind of considerations have
they made of the role of Consciousness
right um so I I I'll just bring some
some something in so
that so when we talk about qualia uh
epiphenomenalism um um and uh what it is
like um like in the bat um what is like
to be a bad Thomas nle when we are or or
the the hard problem of Consciousness
when we talk about that we are within a
certain conceptual
toolkit right we are already within what
wienstein would call a bottle a theory
right and it's important to to to
understand that when we
start making our way within a
theoretical path it's like we're
building blocks of a house and then we
getting a certain kind of house by
virtue of the the belief system thoughts
that and the path that we are
doing that's the kind of like conceptual
Machinery that you get once you play
that game so and by playing that game
I'm here referring to or having in mind
viin Stein's language games so you can
tell the story of
or you can do the epistemology of
understanding uh how cognition comes
around and about and works by playing
different games and that is the
traditional analytic philosophy of Mind
Game and that game is very associated
with the computational theory of mind so
what I'm trying to say here is that once
you put on certain goggles there are
certain things that you're going to see
and there are certain things that you
cannot see
so once you start on that path of
thinking Journey those are the problems
that you're going to find those are the
problems that like the hard problem of
Consciousness is a problem that you're
going to find because then what you get
is uh how do we study both the easy
problem and the hard problem so you
necessarily when you start going in that
direction you find those problems and
then you have the explanatory Gap that
how we close the gap so these are
problems that come up within the
computational theory thinking language
game so those are the goggles
right and of course we can try to make
these theories talk to each other but
it's very important to understand that
it's almost like axiomatic in the sense
that you start solving an equation in
one way it the equation will look a
certain way you start solving the
equation in a different way the equation
will look in a in a different way right
so that's almost what we are talking
about right because we are not starting
from the point in E cognition doesn't
start from the point of view of the
brain in the other um more traditional
computational theor of M of course it
does so once you do start from the bra
brain being machine note what questions
come up okay so if the brain is a
machine then how is it that it gives
rise so it's a scaling up problem how is
it that it gives a rise to Consciousness
how does this machine give rise to
Consciousness because there are there is
evidence that there's Consciousness that
is what it is like to be about there's
qualia there's a hard problem of
Consciousness this is within that kind
of thinking because you start by the
brain being a machine and then you ask
how do we get to the good stuff and then
you get all of that from within the more
radical e cognitive science you don't
start from the brain being a machine
that's the first thing you reject right
and that's also in dynamical and complex
systems theory the case you have
phenomenal work by Van Helder and other
people that precisely reject that
cognition has anything to do of being
anywhere or we should use any conceptual
uh any concept from a computational
scientist perspective to Kit right so
then you don't start from there you
start from the point of view that living
systems are precarious and they engage
with the world to maintain themselves
the brain is part of the story but you
don't start there right so in this
engagement what happens is you have you
engage with the world because you have
certain goals usually the goals have to
do in a more minimalistic biology way is
that you don't want to die it's the
precariousness of of pushing back on the
second law of Thermodynamics right so
you engage in the world for that reason
because you want to remain alive
typically this is the most basic biology
there's much more than that but let's
just stay with that so then what happens
is you start exploring the world and in
exploring the world you do that by
exploring your body so that's when the
body comes in as the body is the means
by which you have access and explore the
world and respond to the world's and
invitations to exploration so it is in
these interactions with the world that
are extremely embodied and limited
they're both constrained and possible by
the body that whatever you do it's
cognitive behavior and this cognitive
behavior is what are the goods that we
want to understand in cognitive science
and we do that by by explaining them
through patterns of behavior right so
it's completely different
goggles yeah I I am going to push back
because I think it's I think it's good
it's not adversarial it's collaborative
um I I just sense or I just kind of
believe that the Vicken styan relativism
has its has its limits right it has its
points where you say well there are
certain things that maybe aren't
relative in the language game and maybe
one of those are the fundamental aspects
of my experience that I can attest
to regardless of if I'm in a braid of
lat or if I'm an evil demon is tricking
me right like unless I adopt some
illusionism about Consciousness which
I'm not willing to do but again like
it's not there there's not a viable
position to do but I'm going to take it
for granted that like even even radical
illusionists wouldn't say that qualia
doesn't exist it's just not what we
think it is and I'm think here Kei
Frankish and den it so for me like the
Vick steinan relativism that qualia is
itself part of a um Paradigm to use a
sort of term of Thomas [ __ ] or it's part
of a boss or it's part theoric yes in
the sense of the linguistic aspect of it
but the fundamental phenomenon is at
least for what I can tell is real so
what is the alternative I guess is my
question right yet I I I don't I'm not
refuting the notion that a cognition is
in some way constrained and opened up
impossibility by having a body by being
embedded in the social context and so on
but we still have to GR in my opinion we
still have to grasp with the fundamental
facts of phenomenal experience so I'm
sorry if I sound like David Charmers and
David Charmers parrot but no it seems to
me that like I can't get away from the
explanatory Gap and I don't think that
that's a problem in my theoretical
framing of the problem I think
that's because the phenomena phenomena
associated with Consciousness is so
radically different from anything else
in the physical Universe yeah and and
there are very um I must say that there
are very good points that are made by
David chalas in that respect that I that
I uh very much um agree with
um now to go back to that and to link
that in a way that would be um that
would be compatible within uh my view of
an
activism I would say that and also
wienstein
um there is a real world that you don't
have access
to so I completely agree with what you
said right I completely agree uh that
there is a limit to relativism yes
that's the limit the limit is the limits
of my view I'm not going to say the
limits of my language as which I did in
the first in the first book in trus
because you overcame that so I'm just
going to um I'm going to dare to
reformulate that for him and say the
limits of my perspective are my world so
there's there there there are aspects of
the world that I will not have access
to and that's just the way things are I
will not have access to your experience
of the world because and here's the
inactivist bit coming in because my
experience
is determined
by the set of past interactions that
I've had with the world and this moment
right here where um this experience is
taking place and everything else outside
of this I don't have access
to that's the bit in the Bo in in the
box right
so the the the idea is not the rejection
of other perspectives and that's
precisely vien Stein's point is
understanding understanding that there
are it's the humility of understanding
that there are other perspectives in the
world and you do not have access to them
you only have access to your own uh very
um specific kind of perspective to the
world now another thing that he adds
that it may be uh useful um is to say
that for him these
are seen in terms of aspects of the
world you see the world through the
aspects that are made relevant to you
right here right now given what given
your past experiences your past
interactions of the world that's why
certain things will become
Salient in this particular moment in the
environment which connecting to the
other Theory you would call the what it
is like to be me to what it is like see
I don't know if I would
um the well to me I wouldn't right I
mean the the salience of my environment
I completely agree is shaped by my body
it's shaped by my homeostatic
requirements it's shaped by my
sociocultural upbringing status and so
on but the fact of the matter is is that
things we could describe things as being
Salient without necessarily
invoking well that's a good question I
guess whether we could invoke salience
of out Consciousness but I guess I I
mean as a force experiment you
can in a sense um I had John Vu on last
week and he was talking about relevance
realization and so it's very sort of
still fresh in my mind I said my my
reading of this would be that salience
is just a manifestation of the conscious
experience itself but are we going to
get any closer to the actual fundamental
characteristics right like whether it's
salience or visual perception or
auditory perception I mean like the
Charmers problem is still there
right uh the Chara's problem is okay
let's let me just go back to the initial
thing because otherwise I'll lose it um
that you said um um the the note that
the difference between the Frameworks is
quite it's quite this simple thing which
is Things become relevant and Salient
and experienced in a certain way within
ecognition because of the embodied
experiences that you've had in the past
within a computational theory of mind
you might say the same you might say
things are relevant what it is like to
be me why well because of the way that
information has been process processed
in the brain as a as a as a machine so
these are different explanations for the
same kind of phenomenon they're diff
they are completely different so this is
where they are aart
right um now as to the problem of um the
heart I think when you said Chara
problem you meant the heart problem of
Consciousness right um y okay so it may
be the case and this is also a Vian sign
move so I'm not going to take credit for
that um uh it may be the case and this
is very in line with with David chers
which is why I think there are certain
features of it of of of chmer thinking
that I that I really like and agree with
um vians makes this point not everything
that is there to be understood about the
mind can be understood through the
scientific
meod and this is the hard problem of
consciousness that chmer talks about
right and and I think that he makes a
good point there I think that he is very
um cever and very very correct and I
completely agree with three points that
he makes which is that many people are
falling up on the Trap of claiming to
study Consciousness and experience and a
first person however you want to call it
depending on the theory you're coming
from um embodiment if you like they
claim to study embodiment and conscious
experience and all of those kind of like
good things that really make
us by going to the brain Alone by
studying easy stuff and that is a
theoretical trap it's a fallacy and
that's where I really agree with with
David charma's work which is why I'm
doing what I'm doing in in ecognition
precisely because I do not want to get
into that trap which I think it's it's a
trap as well I agree with him great
wonderful well that's our that's our
convergence point and again I it's it's
it's not so much that we need to solve
the hard problem but I'm just curious
about whether it retains its problematic
nature in in for so that that that's
good to get some clarity on that I Rend
I wonder just it it's it's a difficult
question but and again I'm not trying to
get you to solve the whole problem I'm
just curious about your thoughts on this
I said I had John Vu on last week and
he's got this idea that getting more
precise on the f function of
Consciousness would help us in
resolving the nature of Consciousness
the hard problem do you see any
viability in that
link you can get some something by the
function if you within the Frameworks
that I work on active inference and
activism right Within These Frameworks
I'm going to give the answer within
these Frameworks you can get some
explanatory traction you can get some um
epistemic virtue out of thinking
function but it doesn't get you all the
way through it gets you to understand
the precariousness and why systems
behave in the way that they do it's
because they the function is that they
want to push back on the second law of
Thermodynamics they want to remain alive
but then you think about a point that
Simon DEA made which is also a very
clever point which is if all that is to
life is to not to
perish then what is it that makes us
different to
vegetation right so function gives you
as much as it's interesting and relevant
to the point that it explains or it
gives you as far as a cross life
explanation so one thing that you get is
the function is all life does not want
to die typically That's the Law that's
the that's the free energy principle
that's
all but it gets you as far as that and
you want more
because you want to get to the goods of
like uh embodied experience right why
people behaving the way that they do
right so here I think
that you can bring in also again some on
the above wise is is is I think is a
good segue into um making this point
which is very under the E umbrella but I
think she makes this point in in a way
that here is it's going to make the
point um clearer which is that if if
again going back to the point if all
that is to life is not to perish then
what makes us different from vegetation
what makes us different from vation is
that we are in um a kind of cognitive
development trajectory that we become
enculturated we are situated in Social
cultural
environments and once that happens we
start behaving in ways that not only do
we get the conceptual toolkits the
reasoning Etc but we also have access
and contribute and Co construct those
social environments from the very
embodied situation that we are at so in
a way the biological body constraints
the access and co-construction that you
do with the world as well as the social
culturally developed embodiment also
plays a role in the participation that
you have or not have within the
environment that you navigate now she
puts this in terms
of uh the living being between it's it's
a condition between freedom and
facticity which see how how compatible
this is with what we were saying about
push pushing back on the on the second
law of Thermodynamics you want to remain
alive but you don't want to remain alive
within an encapsulated environment you
want to remain alive and do really well
in a social cultural environment which
is why we are more than simple
vegetation that just wants to leave we
want to live well we want to live good
we want to do things that are good for
us so we start now entering the realm of
reasons like reasons that we need to
give for the things that we do in the
ways that we act right so now we start
to become very sophisticated start to
get to this like uh mental
representation if you will but it
doesn't come for free it's not a
commodity we we now we start getting
into like season 3 right which is like
things start to get like really
interesting so then you can explain
um embodied experience as being social
culturally
situated that is dependent on the
embodiment that you have and that
embodiment that you have is what is
going to somehow determine where you are
navigating continuously between freedoms
and
facticity and she puts it even more
precisely between um agency and
objectification and then you start
reasons to how you navigate the social
cultural World wonderful yeah yeah it's
the first time I've had s b brought up
in intive inference conversation but um
she that that's great uh yeah it's a
wonderful segue actually into
existentialism and phenomenology and and
we're big fans of mlo Ponte and haiger
and draus on this on this podcast as
well I thought what you said was
interesting which is that as you as you
said correctly the free energy principle
is a principle it's like hamiltonian
principle of least action right it's
kind of a where it's it's a first
principles ontological explanation of
just like what in the case of the FY
principle what things have to do if
they're going to continue through time
to
persist but active inference um or in
certain cases predicted processing or in
certain cases computational theories of
mind or in certain cases it activat
theories mind are what we call Process
theories so it's if we take the free
agent principle just to be axiomatically
true in the sense that it's kind of and
I think Carl would say this himself it
if you actually put it down to its nuts
and bolt it doesn't say too much right
it's things do what things have to do to
continue to be the things that they are
really and there's a lot of fun maths
but it's really about how it's
implemented in us or artificial
intelligence or whatever it
is um those process theories become
falsifiable so predicted processing
might not be the right account of uh
continuous St space um active inference
or um perhaps the mind is uh you know
fundamentally Downstream on the body in
in a radically embodied way I guess
because it's
falsifiable um a question that came to
my mind when you were speaking um about
activism is and the history as well of
cognitive science is as you say there's
very few people who will adopt a radical
computational um position these days
daycard John C for example but for
cognitive science is very popular right
to put it
simply can you envisage a future where
for where future science and future
philosophy tell us that viewing the mind
as embodied enacted embedded what was
the last
one go on Wikipedia um yeah is not the
the right way to view it as we now look
back on the computational picture and
think it's
incomplete yeah okay so I I'm going to
go back to the goggles um it it seems
that the ways in so so science is built
on um on First Steps right on the
goggles that you put and then you end up
with certain kinds of um theories that
now you have and now what would I do
with this I test it I see if it makes
sense right in with the case that it
doesn't make sense uh we we we don't
know but it is about putting these
goggles um
and a lot of what is done still in in
cognitive psychology is very daycard is
very starting in in season 3 in like
okay minds are mental representation so
nobody cares about things that or about
experiments or setting up experiments or
thinking or reasoning about how did it
come to
be right where we we should put more
effort on that how it came to be which
is what by the way dynamical in complex
systems theory applied to psychology
does that's all they do all they do is
to uh focus on the developmental
trajectories to understand how they
evolve and develop how States change
into um developing and evolving um and
and much of what is done in cognitive
psychology is starting in season 3 is
the the mind is representational and now
we got to find that not only in our
cognitive psychology experiments as we
put as we as we design our experiments
right is with that assumption in place
and that's why this is so dangerous it
may be the case that one is right to
think that the mark of the mental is
mental
representation but not criticizing it
and not having a critical point of view
about it what what it means is that
everything that we do within cognitive
science science within setting up
experiments within setting up
computational models simulations it's
going to be starting with the assumption
that the mark of the mental is mental
representation and that the brain is an
information processing machine so this
is going to be defining for everything
that we do and all that I'm saying is
that let's take a step back and go to
the beginning of the series as opposed
to starting in in in season three and
question these things and if they still
make sense great we've done a very good
job right so so that's that's the point
of view right and I think that what
ecognition the more radical view does is
it takes away that those toys and puts
you into okay when you have to start
from the very beginning what do you have
and how do you build so it it it puts
things into into
pressure on whether that is the case
because when you do the bit of the
history of philosophy of mind and you
realize that a lot of it has been done
by borrowing conceptual toolkits from
computational science then you ask the
question what is left for philosophy of
mind is there a philosophy of mind or is
there a borrowing conceptual toolkit
from computer
science now that is a that's a
provocative question I'm not going to
I'm not going to try and answer it it it
it's cool the way you talk about the the
scientific theories it reminds me we had
ma alberon as our second guest and
actually on the day of us calling this
the podcast just came out so everyone
should definitely go and watch it but we
had a long chat about epistemic
communities and the kind of silos that
people end up in and that's actually
very much akin to what you were saying
that people can really end up stuck in
their scientific Paradigm and I'm really
hoping that doesn't happen to
me I think it's kind of happening
already I mean it makes me think the my
my sort of um philosophy science is not
as good as it should be and it should
get better but I'm aware of Thomas C in
this idea of the Paradigm the way it
sounds to me is that like I don't know
I'm adopting a kind of more heelan
perspective where um you got the
computational theory of the mind and in
activism like radical in activism as
your thesis um and your sort of
antithesis and you have this dialectical
relationship right and then what you
might end up with is a
symphysis and that might I don't know
it's a very broad question but do you
see science unfolding in that
or is it kind of more of a incremental
Pursuit towards a higher or or getting
closer to truth so um yeah you do have
those two different paradigms and I
would answer that in in in in in a in a
very clear way I think that all that we
have in the computational theory of mind
is our human social culturally situated
experience as a human species best
efforts to understand
a phenomenon in the natural world so we
develop all this computational Machinery
strategies models Etc because we this is
what makes us human we want to
understand the world around us and part
of the world around us is human beings
right so then we we have all of that as
a reflection or as telling or as a
manifestation of what we can do as a
species when we come down to being
epistemic communities and these
epistemic communities are and ma was
absolutely right are completely social
culturally
situated so uh science itself like our
own individual experience of the world
does not occure in an encapsulated
manner we could aim for an ideal bird ey
view
perspective of being doing science in a
way that is completely objective but as
wienstein already told us we don't have
that we cannot get out of the trajectory
that brought us here we cannot have
access to that other perspective only
our own and that is going to be biased
and overlooking that it's dangerous
because one would claim that that that
is possible and that's not that's why
our best our best um capacity as a human
species is these epistemic communities
where we can exchange ideas test ideas
with each other give feedback to each
other and improve each other's thinkings
and um an experiment such that we
improve in a collective effort that is
scientific wonderful I like that it's
spiriting I don't like the idea that
we're just stepping on the the toes of
our ancestors maybe they did have
something good to tell us and we can
build together but maybe never get there
because we're blinded in some sense I
mean um obviously where one cannot speak
therefore one must be silent um in this
case we could go on forever um I do want
to make it clear that your work is
incredibly Broad and diverse and touches
on a wonderful range of things so we
could have spoken about religion you
have a wonderful paper on religion from
an act of inference perspective um
autism among other things uh we didn't
even touch upon artificial intelligence
agents um so there's going to have to be
around two I
suppose it there's where can people find
your work what are you working on what
have you got coming out where can people
find you because I'm sure they'll want
to know more about what you're doing
yeah just on my website that's usually
what is updated um which is www. energy
poo.com so usually there you got the
links to other places like Publications
Etc and on Twitter as well I'm usually
active so anything that comes out uh any
uh conference that I'm organizing
participating or papers that are out I
always share them on on on my Twitter so
that's usually the places super great
okay that's wonderful well it's half
past 11 UK p.m. so I need to need to
dash off to bed but this has been an
absolute pleasure um it thank you so
much for your time and yeah as I said we
should definitely do this again oh thank
you so much what a terrific uh exciting
uh uh conversation thank you so much and
definitely up for round two well
thank you thank you